Preliminary Guide to the Silvain van Praet Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Silvain van Praet papers
1914-1918
MS 1241
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.5
Principally a manuscript diary kept in English in twelve school notebooks by Silvain van Praet, a member of the Ostend (Belgium) city government, from the day of the German occupation of Ostend (1914 October 14) until its liberation (1918 October 17). It was concealed in a hole in the wall of the Maison Communal. There is also a typescript copy of the manuscript (568 p.) and several related documents.
Praet, Silvain van
Existence and Location of Copies
Entire collection is also available on microfilm (989 frames on 1 reel, 35mm.) from Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library, at cost. Order no. HM229.
Biographical / Historical
Silvain van Praet was a member of the city government in Ostend, Belgium. He kept a diary during the 1914-1918 German occupation of the city.
Scope and Contents
Principally a manuscript diary kept in English in twelve school notebooks by Silvain van Praet, a member of the Ostend (Belgium) city government, from the day of the German occupation of Ostend (1914 October 14) until its liberation (1918 October 17). It was concealed in a hole in the wall of the Maison Communal. There is also a typescript copy of the manuscript (568 p.) and several related documents.
Conditions Governing Access
The entire collection is available on microfilm. Patrons must use FILM HM 229 instead of the originals.
World War, 1914-1918 -- Personal narratives; World War, 1914-1918 -- Belgium; Belgium -- History -- German occupation, 1914-1918; Ostend (Belgium); Diaries; Praet, Silvain van
- Inventory
  - Diaries
    - 1914 Oct 14-Dec 25 (Box 1, Folder 1, Reel 1U)
    - 1914 Dec 26-1915 Mar 14 (Box 1, Folder 2, Reel 1U)
    - 1915 Mar 14-Jul 4 (Box 1, Folder 3, Reel 1U)
    - 1915 Jul 5-Nov 5 (Box 1, Folder 4, Reel 1U)
    - 1915 Nov 6-Dec 7 (Box 1, Folder 5, Reel 1U)
    - 1915 Dec 8-1916 Jan 12 (Box 1, Folder 6, Reel 1U)
    - 1916 Jan 16-Jun 2 (Box 1, Folder 7, Reel 1U)
    - 1916 Jun 21-Sep 24 (Box 1, Folder 8, Reel 1U)
    - 1916 Sep 25-1917 Feb 23 (Box 1, Folder 9, Reel 1U)
    - 1917 Feb 24-Sep 19 (Box 1, Folder 10, Reel 1U)
    - 1917 Sep 19-1918 Apr 30 (Box 1, Folder 11, Reel 1U)
    - 1918 May 14-Oct 17 (Box 1, Folder 12, Reel 1U)
  - TMS, "The Occupation of Ostend by the Germans, 1914-1918 (Box 1, Folder 13 - 18, Reel 1U)
  - Albert I, King of the Belgians: proclamations, 1914, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 19, Reel 1U)
  - Miscellaneous documents, 1914-1918, undated (Box 1, Folder 20, Reel 1U)